A Guide to the Naomi Sokol Zeavin Collection on Mason District History, 1992-2012
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Naomi Sokol Zeavin Collection on Mason District History, 1992-2012
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-66
1.0 linear feet
The Naomi Sokol Zeavin Collection on Mason District History consists of 1.0 linear feet and spans the years 1992-2012 and contains biographical papers, history notebooks containing research on various Mason District topics, DVD films produced by Zeavin, historical maker announcements and programs, and other Mason District history research by Michael McCullen and Carolyn Kinney.
Zeavin, Naomi Sokol (1933-)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Naomi Sokol Zeavin on April 4, 2007; and additions on May 16, 2018
Historical and Biographical Information
Naomi Delores Sokol was born in New Britain, Connecticut on March 12, 1933. She graduated from Dean Academy in Franklin, Massachusetts in 1951, and studied Speech and Drama at Emerson College in Boston, Massachusetts. She married Dr. Bernard H. Zeavin on September 12, 1954 in New Britain and the couple moved to Lake Barcoft in Falls Church, Virginia in 1959.
In 1980-1984, Governor John Dalton appointed Zeavin to serve on the Board of Visitors for the Schools for the Deaf and the Blind. Governor George Allen later appointed her to the Board of People with Disabilities, and Tom Davis selected her to serve on the Fairfax County Advisory Board of Social Services. Zeavin also served as an appointee of the Advisory Committee to the United States Civil Rights Commission for Virginia.
Zeavin was a Virginia delegate to the Republican National Convention in 1976 and 1980, and campaigned for 14 years to get Ronald Reagan elected into the White House. On May 14, 1985, President Reagan appointed her to the Advisory Committee on the Arts to the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts.
In 1994, Supervisor Tina Trapnell appointed Zeavin to the Fairfax County History Commission as a representative of the Mason District, a position which she held until the end of 2016. While on the commission, she helped fundraise and erect six historical markers. She also wrote many articles on Fairfax County history and undertook research on the Bailey, Munson, Mason and Clark families of Mason District. The Historical Society of Fairfax County published her article “The Bailey Family: From Menagerie to Crossroads” in Volume 28 of their 2001-2002 yearbook. Her research debunked the myth that there once was a circus at Bailey’s Crossroads. While on the commission, she also produced several videos on the history of Fairfax County.
Zeavin served as a board member and past president of the Capitol Hill Civil War Roundtable, and was the Guest Curator at the Clark House in Falls Church from 2000-2006. In 2008, she published the book “Carmen's Secret Diary: Aboard the USS Hornet (CV-12) in 1944”. Zeavin is president of UR Unique, a marketing and public relations firm, in Falls Church, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Naomi Sokol Zeavin Collection on Mason District History consists of 1.0 linear feet and spans the years 1992-2012 and contains biographical papers, history notebooks containing research on various Mason District topics, DVD films produced by Zeavin, historical maker announcements and programs, and other Mason District history research by Michael McCullen and Carolyn Kinney. Subjects include Baileys Crossroads and the Mason District of Fairfax County.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
Original notebook binders were removed
Index Terms
Baileys Crossroads (Va.) - History; Mason District (Fairfax County, Va.) - History; Zeavin, Naomi Sokol (1933-)
Container List
- Biographical papers on Naoimi Sokol Zeavin, 1992-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Historical Marker announcements, programs, and press, 1999-2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Booklet, “A Guide to the Historic Markers of Mason District”, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Handout, Where to Find Mason District History Resource Materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Notebook, African American History at Baileys Crossroads, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Notebook, Bailey Family History, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Notebook, Celebrating Gladys Bushrod’s Life, African American History, Gunston Area and Fairfax County Schools, Shiloh Baptist Church and Cemetery, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Notebook, Corrections to Elephants and Quaker Guns, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Notebook, Historic Photographs of Mason District, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Notebook, Listing and Description of the ten programs on the history of the area, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Notebook, Mason Hill, Clark House and Other Historical Highlights, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Notebook, Munson Family History, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Notebook, Video Scripts of Zeavin, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Notebook, When Mason District Was Formed, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- “A Brief History of the Fire Service in Mason District Fairfax County” by Michael McCullen, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Binder, “Salute to our Heroes: History of Fairfax County Police Department and Mason District Station” by PFC Carolyn Kinney, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- DVD, “Interview with Ed Bearss on the Civil War” [29 min], 1992 (Box 2)
- DVD, “Jeb Stuart on Munsons Hill” [22 min], 1992 (Box 2)
- DVD, “Fairfax County USA” [27 min], 1996 (Box 2)
- DVD, “The Civil War Trail in Mason District”, [26 min], 2003 (Box 2)
- DVD, “Historic Mason District” [27 min], 2004 (Box 2)
- DVD, “Mason District Supervisors Speak Out” [27 min], 2004 (Box 2)
- DVD, “Celebration of African American History” [26 min], 2005 (Box 2)
- DVD, “The Collins & Lee Story”,[26 min], 2006 (Box 2)
- DVD, “Fairfax County’s 5th Annual History Conference”, 2009 (Box 2)
- DVD, “Mason Hill’s Civil War Historic Marker”, Undated (Box 2)
- DVD, “The Amazing Gladys Cook Bushrod”, Undated (Box 2)